[Music]
hello everybody it's great to be back
with you today we discuss afghanistan
so let me first take a look at who all
is with us i can see somnath abhilash
krishna saraf
good evening good day everybody it's
great to be with you again
so as always i am going to take a number
of questions that you all have asked
in the comments
so i'm going to take more than 20 25
questions and after that if there is
time i will take some live questions
and as you know we are talking about
afghanistan today things are changing
very rapidly in afghanistan and taliban
have
more or less taken over the country most
of the country
more than 90 of it
and things are changing fast things are
evolving so that is what we discussed
today you have you all have asked a
great number of
a lot of questions very interesting
questions
so let us get into it with question
number one
okay aka the guy asks
what is the relation between the taliban
and the pashtuns
good question so the taliban
are overwhelmingly pashtuns
i would say that more than 90 99 of the
taliban are from the pashtun ethnicity
so that is the relationship between the
taliban and the pashtuns i would not say
that all the pashtuns are taliban only a
few of them are taliban but the vast
majority the overwhelming majority of
the taliban
are
of pashtun ethnicity so that is the
relationship between the taliban and the
pashtuns which is very interesting
because afghanistan is home to a number
of ethnic groups
the pashtuns are the
original inhabitants the true natives of
afghanistan
but there are a number of other ethnic
groups in afghanistan as well the
taliban
are almost exclusively
pashtuns so that's an interesting thing
to note as we begin this
discussion this conversation
question number two
any sources that pashtuns are people
from the indian subcontinent many people
say that pashtuns are a lost israeli
tribe there are three main ethnic groups
in the region persians tajiks
uzbeks turkmens khazaras and pakistanis
who are indians etc
listen i'm not going to give you sources
this is a discussion that's a
conversation if i bring sources and i do
all that then i'm going to be able to
answer only three or four questions so i
can show you the way but you need to do
a little bit of homework right so yes
the pashtuns are an extension of the
population of the indian subcontinent
they are much the same as us they have
the same origin as the indian people
they are an extension they are the
ancient people of gandhar of the
mahabharat times now there is a lot of
research that shows this genetic
research linguistic research etc you can
look it up the information is available
in the public domain so the sources are
available in the public domain do a
little bit of research thank you
now yes the pashtuns many people claim
that the pashtuns are a lost israeli
tribe many pashtuns themselves believe
that they are the descendants of a lost
israeli tribe
right
now genetic research has disproved this
conclusively
genetic research demonstrates that the
push stones are
an extension of the population of the
indian subcontinent there is absolutely
not even a small trace of any israeli or
jewish ancestry
among the pashtun people
okay so this is a myth that they seem to
believe for whatever reason you know
when
it's it's something you see not only in
afghanistan not only among the pashtuns
but also in various converted people in
india in the indian subcontinent
especially pakistan and other places
for example the pakistanis many of them
they promote this fairy tale that they
are the descendants of either turks or
arabs initially they used to claim that
they are the descendants of arabs now
the arabs don't like it and they have
made it very clear that they don't see
the pakistanis as their own so now the
pakistanis are trying to invent
a descent from the turks
they are trying to find affinity with
the turkish people
so this is a fairy tale that they make
up in order to
differentiate themselves
from the people of the indian
subcontinent especially from the hindus
because they feel that
they need some sort of
basis or foundation to their two nation
theory claim
so the truth is that the dna is the same
but dna doesn't make a nation dna is
very different from culture the dna can
be the same but culture is different so
so there is no basis to this claim that
the pashtuns are a lost israeli tribe
apart from that yes there are many other
ethnic groups the persians the who are
targets so let me show the map to
illustrate
these things
the map as always helps us understand
things better
okay so this is the map
let me remove this okay
so this is afghanistan as you can see to
the south of afghanistan and to the east
of afghanistan you have pakistan and
india
okay
to the north over here you have
tajikistan
so the tajik people are essentially an
indo-iranian people they speak uh i
think they speak persian
a form of persian maybe it's variant of
persian so they are an indo-iranian
people
so there are those are the tajik people
this region of afghanistan which is to
the north which borders tajikistan
has a significant uh
tajik population so that is the tajik
minority of afghanistan
then
if you go east to uh to the west of
afghanistan northwest you have
uzbekistan and turkmenistan
so you have
in the regions of afghanistan that
border these two countries you have
significant populations
of uzbek ethnicity and turkmen ethnicity
and to the south you have balochistan to
the west you have iran so you have this
this nice interesting
cocktail of ethnicities in afghanistan
the original ethnicity the natives of
afghanistan are of course the pashtun
people who speak the pashto language
so that is
so that's the fact about the
uh ethnicities that you find within
afghanistan you have the pashtuns and
you have all these other ethnicities as
well including the hazaras the hazaras
are not turks the hazaras are the
descendants
of the soldiers of chingas khan ching is
khan
left behind some soldiers after
fighting
the
the runaway jalaluddin kharismi in the
battle of the indus exactly 800 years
ago so he came through afghanistan which
was then gandhar part of india and then
he went back through that region but he
left behind a garrison of soldiers and
commanders
and their descendants are today's
hazaras the hazaras claim they have
always been in afghanistan but genetics
tells us a different story
so that is the uh ethnic mix in
afghanistan that is important to note to
understand the entire conflict that's
happening that's unfolding as we speak
right now
so jatin kumar asks when was the why was
the taliban formed that's of a very good
question who created the taliban and why
was the taliban created right
so to understand this you have to go
back a few decades
so
in 1979 in the end of 1979 the ussr the
soviet union invaded afghanistan from
the north let me show you the map
okay so so you have these countries
turkmenistan uzbekistan tajikistan these
were all part of the ussr
now the ussr the soviet union sought to
increase
its geopolitical footprint they wanted
to expand their sphere of influence
and
they were very of the us presence in
pakistan
and they were afraid that the they would
the americans would also start
influencing afghanistan because
afghanistan
was to some extent in the urban areas of
westernized country
so to offset this possibility the
soviets invaded afghanistan in 1979 in
late 1917
in autumn and winter of that year
now the invasion was not very well
planned it was not very successful the
americans what they did was they
they
basically they helped pakistan they gave
aid in the form of
money millions and millions of dollars
and in the form of weaponry
and they encouraged pakistan they
assisted pakistan in creating these
terrorist outfits called the mujahideens
one would not call them terrorists at
that point in time because their purpose
was to
fight off the invading soviet union
so what when the soviets invaded
afghanistan lots of afghan refugees came
into pakistan at that time the dictator
of pakistan was
and he had islamized pakistan thoroughly
by the time he had changed the education
system he had promoted
thousands of madrasahs and all these
afghan students who came into
to pakistan as refugees they studied in
this madrasas and these madrasas were
the
recruiting grounds for all these
mujahideens so the mujahideens were
armed with weapons made that the
americans provided
and they were infiltrated back into
afghanistan to find the u to fight the
ussr in guerrilla warfare so this
guerrilla warfare warfare went on for
nearly a decade
and it was a war of attrition it was
exhausting for the soviets because the
pakistanis kept on pushing in arms
ammunition supplies
and mujahideen fighters through the
porous northern borders and the soviets
just could not cope with it because the
pakistanis had an unlimited amount of
supplies and and support from the u.s
so there was a proxy war in afghanistan
which eventually the pakistanis or the
u.s won the soviets retreated out of
afghanistan within a decade's time
now
what happened was that these mujahideen
fighters
they suddenly found themselves fighting
each other
and
and what the pakistanis did was that
they
redirected many of these foreign
fighters into kashmir
and that was the genesis of the kashfi
kashmir terrorism 1989 the indian
government was very weak at the time it
looks like they did not do much to
prevent it now
this is what happened
in the
1990s
the northern alliance and various other
factions of the mujahideen had formed a
government in afghanistan in kabul
burhan
rabbani was the president then you had
sigma mujadi
and various other
war lords
who wide amongst each other for
influence now the pakistanis
they have a long term objective their
objective their dream their great dream
is to one day
wage a great war with india reclaim
kashmir and destroy india islamize india
that is their great dream that is
pakistan's great dream and they
hatched this plan to use afghanistan as
a recruiting ground for their
long dreamed of war with india
so they wanted they decided to to
use afghanistan as their strategic
backyard
and
they created this outfit called the
taliban they recruited the taliban
fighters from the madrasas there are
thousands of madrasas in pakistan and
the students there are called talibs
in the arabic language so
the plural of taleb is taliban
so these were the taliban fighters that
the pakistanis
recruited from the from the madrasas
and many of these leaders were the
mujahideen who had fought against the
ussr they suddenly found themselves out
of a job because the only thing they
knew was how to fight
so the mujahideen leaders became the
leaders of the taliban many of them
and
these
young students who were studying in the
motherhood of pakistan
they became the fighters of the taliban
and this was a proxy war the pakistanis
supplied these taliban fighters with
arms ammunition weaponry funds etc and
very soon in the mid 1990s the taliban
were able to quickly
take over afghanistan and they were able
to form a government in kabul there so
this is why the taliban was formed and
this is how the taliban was formed it is
the creation of the isi the pakistani
isi it was a brainchild of one of the
uh
one of the one of the directors of the
isi and of benazir bhutto
benazir bhutto is the one
who along with the isi with tacit u.s
understanding and approval they formed
the taliban
to turn afghanistan into pakistan's
strategic backyard to give pakistan
strategic depth their intention is to
one day fight a great war with india
and use afghans
as the cannon fodder that is the reason
why the taliban was formed and that is
how the taliban was formed so because of
this pakistani support the taliban was
able to take out afghanistan in the
1990s i think it was 96 i believe
more or less
and they were able to form a government
it was a brutal regime as we know and
then many other things happened but this
is why and how the taliban was formed it
was a creation of the
pakistani government and the isi and it
had the support and the approval of the
united states
okay next question is
by harsh
can you elucidate the different talibans
that is afghan and
aliban pakistan
and their objectives and plans towards
pakistan and india have they joined
hands now or
were they always aligned
so there are two talibans like you say
there is the taliban itself the main
taliban who are now in power in
afghanistan and then you have the tariq
taliban pakistan which is a separate
organization
so what is the genesis of the territory
in pakistan what is the genesis of the
pakistani taliban
so after the 9 11 bombings after the
americans invaded and occupied
afghanistan many of the taliban fighters
etc many of the mujahideens they crossed
over into pakistan into the
into the fatah region federally
administered tribal areas which is the
pashtun areas of pakistan
and many of these people who crossed
over were actually foreign fighters
arabs and what not
so the americans started bombing these
regions of pakistan using drone strikes
and all that
and the pakistan army also with the
approval of the tribal elders
they came into this region
with the ostensible aim of flushing out
the foreign fighters but what the
pakistani army did was they acted like
an occupying army they started burning
villages and killing people
so
this region rebelled against the
americans and the pakistanis and the
mujahideens were who were already there
they combined forces and came up with
this new taliban that the taliban
pakistan that is in very short what
happened this was in the early 2000s
2003 to 2005 thereabouts
and that is the birth of the tereki
taliban pakistan so that is a separate
organization from the afghan taliban the
main taliban the territory is an
umbrella organization of a large number
of small to medium-sized terrorist
outfits and resistance outfits their
objective is to resist the united states
and the pakistan army both
so the taliban pakistan their activities
are largely confined to pakistan itself
these are terrorist activities they have
been fighting with the pakistani state
the punjabistan state the pakistani army
and the isi
and to some extent they are also
cooperating at times with the isi it's a
complicated situation the tariqah
taliban pakistan also has very close
ties with the so-called al-qaeda even
with the islamic state isis
in a way it's very hard to differentiate
between the territory pakistan and the
al-qaeda and the isis these are tags
that foreigners have put upon them
they have the same objectives they have
the same ideology
it's very hard to actually see any
difference between these different
organizations so that is the tahrir
pakistan
at times they have aligned with the
afghan taliban
they even had an agreement at at some
point in time but for most of their
existence that the taliban pakistan has
been in conflict
with
themselves and also with the afghan
taliban
so it has not been a harmonious
relationship
it has been a relationship that has been
filled with conflict and infighting
so they were not always aligned but
recently in the past couple of days one
hears the news
that the pakistani taliban the taliban
pakistan
has
declared its allegiance
to the leadership
to the taliban leadership in kabul
which is a very interesting turn of
events my friends
okay next question dungar singh chauhan
says
i think it's an irony that the us first
created this taliban group and gave them
weapons and what not and then the u.s
trained the afghan army to counter the
taliban i want to know what is the sense
of this that's a very good question
so the us did support the taliban at one
point in time the taliban in its
previous incarnation was the afghan
mujahideen where the freedom fighters if
you watch that movie rambo sylvester
stallone he goes into afghanistan to aid
the mujahideen and to help them liberate
their country from the ussr
so at that time these guys were the
heroes the of ganbuja
then they morphed into the taliban
and the americans
were perfectly fine with that right
isn't it strange the americans were
perfectly fine with that and then
what happened was 9 11 happened so what
happened was that uh there was this
northern resistance fighter northern
alliance uh war lord called ahmad shah
masood who was an ethnic tajik
he was from the panjusher valley
so he was resisting the taliban the
taliban in
in 2001
assassinated him
with a suicide bombing
and two days after ahmad shah massoud's
assassination you had 9 11 the 9 11
terrorist attacks in the united states
in new york
and as far as we know to the best of our
knowledge it was all done by osama bin
laden who was one of the chiefs one of
the leaders of the afghan mujahideen
that were fighting the ussr
so it was done by osama bin laden who
was in afghanistan who was under the
shelter under the protection of the
afghan taliban
the americans
ordered the taliban to hand over osama
bin laden the taliban refused they said
that he is under our protection we have
a code of ethics and honor we will not
give up a person who is our guest and
who is under our shelter
in response the americans invaded and
occupied afghanistan they
well they defeated the taliban
supposedly
what happened after the taliban moved
again into pakistan into
the
tribal areas of pakistan and they sat
there and waited out the time
so they were basically biding their time
for a very long time for more than a
decade they all
many of them were killed many of them
were destroyed but the leadership etc
and many of the fighters they crossed
back into pakistan
and and as you know the americans were
doing drone strikes and all that over
there and that's led to the creation of
the terrorist pakistan
so the americans
first did support the taliban
they supported the afghan mujahide and
then the taliban they knew what was
happening in kashmir they knew that the
pakistanis were routing all these
terrorists into kashmir to destabilize
india and to make india bleed the
americans knew what was happening
and when india complained about this
they said that this is your internal law
and order problem you are unable to take
care of law and order it is not
terrorism it is law and order that's
what the americans would keep repeating
so they knew what was happening
and they supported it the reason for
this is very simple
in the 1990s and early 2000s the us was
still
in its post cold war high
they had won the cold war they had
ensured the disintegration of the soviet
union and they were the only remaining
superpower in the world and india had
dared to declare itself a nuclear power
in 1998 i think
india did five nuclear tests and it
declared itself a nuclear power that was
unacceptable to the u.s how dare this
little country
try and rise up to our level and that's
for that that's why the americans
allowed
and
encouraged the pakistanis to
conduct these terrorist operations into
in india in kashmir and other places
and that is why they allowed the
formation of the taliban and they
basically turned a blind eye towards
that or a benevolent eye towards the
activities of pakistan
pakistan was a u.s
ally pakistan was a u.s puppet so to say
it was an instrument of the us and they
wanted to teach india a lesson and
that's why they encouraged the pakistani
activities of creating these terrorist
outfits a number of terrorist outfits in
kashmir and the taliban itself which
took over afghanistan
so the us was fine with that but after 9
11 happened they had to placate their
local their domestic population the u.s
public and that's why they had to find a
big they had to punish the guys who did
this terrorist attack so that's why they
invaded afghanistan and occupied
afghanistan and then the taliban were
the bad guys because they refused to
hand over osama bin laden
so with the help of pakistan by using
pakistan as a staging base they invaded
afghanistan isn't that interesting
and the pakistanis well what could they
do about it the americans were the
biggest guy in the in the
in the room
you cannot say no to the u.s so the
pakistanis made the best of a bad
situation they
helped the us
and they gained a lot from that in the
form of bribes money
military equipment and all that so it
benefited pakistan
but they kept the taliban alive
in pakistan's tribal areas and the
americans also knew this
so it is it is strange it is ironic but
it is not strange and ionic it all makes
sense if you look at it from the
perspective of of america's interests
america's interest initially was to
uh get rid of the ussr it was to prop up
pakistan as a bulwark against india it
was to punish india for becoming a
nuclear weapons power it was to put
india in its place keep it down by
bleeding it via pakistan
but then when all of this happened when
the 911
9 11 terrorist attacks happened then
they had to punish the taliban
so they went into afghanistan occupied
it defeated so to save the taliban but
kept the taliban alive in pakistan so as
to keep the the pakistani generals on
their side
and then over time as things evolved as
the as we saw the emergence of china
as a serious competitor to the us
as a contender for the superpower
position
that's when the americans slowly started
turning towards india they realized that
the only power in asia that can offset
china that can counter balance china is
india
and that's why slowly slowly
pakistan
became less and less important for the
americans
india became more important and that's
why their policies changed and that's
what we have been witnessing over the
past decade or so so the americans
propped up the afghan army they propped
up an afghan government they held
elections in afghanistan they armed the
afghan army
to fight the taliban but they also kept
the taliban alive
so that is the extremely complicated
mess that is afghanistan but it makes
sense if you look at it from the
prism of geopolitics and from the prism
of america's interests the main actor in
this entire mess is the united states of
america the secondary actor is pakistan
india is an observer and thus far other
nations have been observers but now
things are changing fast
okay donggar singh johan again what is
the source of income of the taliban do
you think they'll be able to sustain
themselves economically so as long as
the taliban were outlaws as long as they
were fighting the us and as long as they
were fighting the afghan army and the
government
their main source they had a number of
sources of income of revenue
number one was drugs they were in
control of these poppy poppy plantations
in the areas they controlled and the
poppy
plant
is turned into i think heroin opm all
that yeah some form of drugs so that was
a major source of revenue i think at
least a quarter of the taliban's revenue
came from
drugs
then you had
taxes they they controlled significant
portions of the country they would levy
taxes then they also had fund funds
coming in from other countries whether
it is from pakistan whether it is from
the saudi arabia from the arabian
countries from oman etc or from other
benefactors and well wishes across the
world they had funds coming in
and they also did extortion they also
had real estate and all that so they had
a number of sources of income they were
able to sustain themselves
now they are in charge of an entire
country
and they have powerful
possible potential allies
they are looking at a relationship with
china they are looking at some sort of
relationship with the russians
maybe pakistan maybe somebody else
so they will be able to sustain
themselves economically especially if
they are
if they are accepted by the
international community is the
legitimate
government of afghanistan
sagar says was the afghan government
corrupt
what was this was this whole dealings in
doha was to give them better weapons
you can't help but laugh when the
journalists were asking taliban about
women's rights wearing a burka herself
that lady from the cnn yes
and all that yeah
so excuse me so your main question is
was the u.s backed
afghan government corrupt
of course it was
i mean there is plenty of uh
evidence out there many many
uh articles have been written about this
about the corruption that you had in the
afghan government whether it was under
mr
mr hamid karzai or whether it was under
mr ashraf ghani it is well known and
well documented that afghan mps members
of parliament
were regularly taking out
plain loads of cash u.s dollars out of
afghanistan to the tune of several
billion dollars per year
this was all usaid money that was
flowing into afghanistan
so all this was happening
that money was being transported out of
the country it was being stashed in bank
accounts
elsewhere
and and so on so yeah it is well known
there were many scams the many real real
estate scams there was a lot of
divergent money many
mps and leaders had these palatial homes
which they lived in they were able to
acquire that sort of money and so on so
it is well known that uh the afghan
government the u.s backed of gun
government was quite corrupt it is well
known
and it is we also know that the
americans were quite aware of this and
this is the modus operandi you know
whether it when whenever the u.s have
propped up a puppet regime anywhere
whether it is afghanistan whether it is
pakistan
whether it is in the in various african
countries whether it was in south korea
initially these were all dictatorial
regimes and extremely corrupt regimes
the pakistani regime the pakistan army
has been up has been propped up by the
us for many many decades and we know how
corrupt they are
so yes the afghan government was quite
corrupt it is not me who is saying this
there are so many articles that have
been written about this it's all out in
the open there is even this allegation
that uh mr ashraf ghani himself tried to
take
several i mean
millions of dollars out of the country
when he fled from the country that is a
claim that has been made i don't know if
it has been proven but that has also
been written about in the past two or
three days
so i think it's quite clear that this
government was corrupt it was designed
to be corrupt
that's the only way you can prop up a
regime that doesn't have
support at the ground level you know
so yes it was corrupt
dungar singh johan asks
earlier the data was saying that the
that there were 300 000 afghan army
soldiers three lakh
who surrendered to the taliban who have
about 75 80 000 soldiers
now the reports are saying the afghan
the actual number of soldiers in the
afghan army was not more than 96 000
and the three lakh soldiers were ghost
soldiers the salaries of these ghost
soldiers were taken by the corrupted
military soldiers is corruption
responsible for the victory of the
taliban
is it legit to blame corruption instead
of the withdrawal of the u.s army
you are right it has now emerged that
the afghan army did not actually have a
strength of 3 lakh 300 000 the strength
was quite a bit below that
the numerical strength
and these are so-called
fictitious ghost soldiers so these
soldiers existed in the army only on
paper
but that money the salaries and all the
funds and equipment and all
that money was diverted
and it was repurposed by various afghan
politicians military leaders warlords
etc yes this is a fact
so the
number the americans and other people
have claimed that the afghan army was
300 000 strong it is a lie it is
completely false
that is point number one was this
corruption responsible for the victory
of the taliban
well one cannot say for sure whether
that is the reason why the taliban won
even if the afghan army was just a
hundred thousand in number or only
nineteen thousand or let's say it was
only ninety thousand in in number
still they would have been able to give
a very strong
opposition and resistance to the taliban
because they were well
even ninety thousand soldiers is a great
number of soldiers it is equal in number
to the taliban and they had superior
weaponry
they had superior equipment they had
better training
and so on so
it doesn't quite explain
why the taliban have been able to take
over the country
in such a lightening fast manner so yes
there is corruption there were all these
ghost soldiers but it does not explain
how
the taliban was able to win
so ridiculously quickly
ashutosh asks what exactly did the u.s
achieve after spending nearly 20 years
and about 100 billion dollars in
afghanistan it's not a hundred billion
dollars it's more than two trillion
dollars
that the
americans spent in afghanistan
so the question you're asking is why did
the americans occupy afghanistan for two
decades well as you as we discussed a
little bit ago a little while ago the
original
aim of the occupation was to uh destroy
the the was to capture osama bin laden
and to punish the people responsible for
the 9 11 terrorist attacks
now they were not able to capture osama
bin laden we know that he moved to
pakistan the pakistanis
orchestrated and engineered that
relocation of the guy into pakistan
in abbottabad so the
initial objective was to
was to bring osama bin laden and the
other his associates to justice it was
to punish the taliban and to
and to bring democracy and freedom and
human rights to afghanistan and
democratic government and
equal rights for women and minorities
and all that yeah
so they were able to do that for 20
years they spent more than two trillion
dollars there many many many thousands
of american soldiers i think i don't
know the exact number but
a lot of american soldiers died there
and a lot of equipment
was transferred to the afghan army
they were trained
so what did the u.s achieve
well the objectives of the u.s changed
america's geopolitical objectives
changed initially they wanted to punish
osama bin laden and the taliban and they
also were very much anti-india when this
entire operation started
in the early 2000s americans were very
much anti-india and pro-pakistan by the
time the americans left they did not
care about pakistan they needed india as
they as of today they need india as a
counterweight to china so the entire
geopolitical equations
have changed
so they achieved
their
initial objective
of uh destroying of defeating the
taliban and eventually they were able to
kill osama bin laden so that was the
objective they wanted to achieve the
secondary objective was to
democratize afghanistan and have a
western style government they achieved
that also to some extent for some time
but as the geopolitical scenario changed
and they found that they have no more
any they no longer have any use for
pakistan or afghanistan they have
left the place so they have achieved
that objective also so
geopolitical objectives are not set in
stone they change with time
and as things changed they changed their
objectives as well
so now they have
left the country because it is
it it suits them
and it serves their interests to leave
the country
so that's what they did in afghanistan
nishant asks
has the u.s really failed in the afghan
scenario
or is the u.s playing another stroke in
this stage of geopolitics to counter
china
as it did against russia in the 1990s
uh yeah so your main question is what is
basically essentially
that is the us withdrawal
a trap for china
so many uh commentators have
written about this spoken about this
that afghanistan
is traditionally has traditionally been
considered to be the graveyard of
empires
starting from the british
they have always
whoever has tried to invade afghanistan
has lost it is not entirely correct that
turks were able to
invade conquer occupy afghanistan and to
change the entire demographics and
culture and religion of afghanistan so
they were able to win they were able to
succeed in that objective but when it
comes to western powers
they have always lost
the british lost
the americans have lost now
and the american calculation possibly is
that they want to now embroil china in
a hopeless cause
and they are hoping and they will
perhaps engineer a scenario in which the
chinese get
bogged down just in the same way that
the ussr got bogged down
in this country and in the long run they
may be hoping that china will also
suffer a catastrophic outcome
in a manner that is similar to what the
ussr had to face so that is a possible
scenario it is a possibility
many geopolitical commentators have
commented about this
so i agree that this is a possibility
rakesh asks
why did the u.s leave a major part of
its arsenal and military vehicles in
afghanistan
was this huge ammunition dumped really
for the afghan soldiers or for the u.s
or has the u.s made secret
internal ties with the taliban and so on
the question you are asking is why did
the u.s leave
such a great deal of military equipment
in afghanistan
well the you if you ask this to the
americans they will say that this was
left behind for the afghan army so that
they could counter the taliban and put
up an effective resistance and prevent
the taliban from taking the country over
so this is the answer the americans will
give us
but as we know this well-trained afghan
army somehow evaporated into thin air
and the taliban took over the country
with astonishing speed
they were saying that that it will take
them 30 days or 90 days to reach kabul
it took them three days
to reach kabul and take over kabul
so what's happened has baffled people
what happened to the afghan army where
did they go
and of course the taliban have been able
to capture all of this military
equipment equipment
billions of dollars of military
equipment vehicles
uh
black hawk helicopters drones
and much much more all the facilities
like the bagram air base and other air
bases
other military facilities the taliban
have taken everything over wholesale
intact
so it is
quite strange and perplexing that the
americans did this
many of these
weapons and supplies were actually being
used by american soldiers american
soldiers were there in afghanistan and
they have withdrawn from there
so
if those
[Music]
equipments and all that were being used
only by americans why were they not
taken back so this is a question that is
currently unanswered
and the americans are are not answering
the question
so it it does seem that there seems
there could be some sort of secret
understanding and there is some kind of
geopolitical game that is being played
at
several levels
who are the principal actors in this
geopolitical game needs to be deciphered
but yes it is quite strange that so much
weaponry so much equipment has just
fallen into the lap of the taliban
you know like like it's a gift from
heaven it is
quite strange indeed
was there any tacit understanding
between the afghan national army and the
taliban because the way they surrendered
in front of the taliban despite having
all the resources
and who is gulbuddin
so what you're asking is did the taliban
and the afghan army have a secret
agreement or some kind of understanding
well we cannot rule that possibility out
because the afghan
army did not
put up any kind of resistance
even if the afghan army was just 90 000
strong they could have held the taliban
back for months and months
with all the equipment the training the
ammunition they had
so they
there were some
token battles
it seems like there were some
show battles you know people firing in
the air making noise for some time an
hour or two and then everything is over
and the taliban moves on
it also appears that many of the afghan
army soldiers
may actually have moved on and switched
sides
and
become part of the taliban regime
it is very much possible it is true that
the taliban have been
targeting some of the commanders of the
afghan army the forces
that is true with unfortunate reports
have come out in in the public domain of
these
incidents happening but the rank and
file of gun soldiers who were part of
the afghan army well where are they
today
that is the big question so it does look
very much like
there was an understanding between the
afghan army especially the pashtun
elements in the afghan army there is a
sizable population of sizable segment of
the afghan army who are pashtuns
there
seems that there was some kind of
agreement between the taliban and the
afghan army
to allow the taliban to take over very
quickly because there is no other way to
explain the rapidity with which the
taliban have taken over the country
after the americans left it's happened
in a blink of an eye
so clearly
clearly there is there was some kind of
understanding between the afghan army
and the taliban
and we are seeing the results of that
who is goloba nickmatyar he is one of
the afghan warlords he was part of the
fighting in the 1990s he was a
part of the pre-taliban government in
afghanistan post
government the northern alliance
etcetera government
and he is a very significant political
player in afghanistan he is a pashtun
ethnic pashtun
he is a warlord he has his own private
personal militia
and that is what gives him political
legitimacy because like mao zedong said
political power flows from the barrel of
a gun and nowhere do you see it more
acutely than in afghanistan
asks
did the afghan army was the afghan army
so weak that they could not they did not
have the confidence to fight the taliban
and do afghan people like to follow
sharia so i've answered the first
question already the question second
question is
do the afghan people desire
sharia law
now recently there was this pew poll pew
survey that was done in afghanistan
which showed that
99 of the people of afghanistan
desire
sharia law in the country
that is a fact
yeah so the people of afghanistan do
desire the imposition of sharia law
99 of the respondents were in favor of
sharia law
and the afghan government the u.s backed
afghan government did not believe in the
sharia law the taliban
believes in the sharia law that is the
only law they follow
so that tells you
something about the sentiment
among
the majority
of the afghan people
today it also to some extent explains
how the taliban have been able to
capture the country so quickly it also
explains
to some extent
why there was so little resistance from
the from the afghan army to the taliban
it also explains to some extent
why
many of the afghan army soldiers may
have now become part of the taliban
the thing is this see my friends
it is
impossible it is futile to impose a
foreign culture
upon a population that does not want it
the americans have been trying to impose
democracy everywhere they tried this in
iraq
they bombed democracy into iraq see what
happened to iraq iraq is a hell hole
today
the living standards
and the
the kind of law and order situation you
had and everything was so much better
under saddam hussein that brutal
dictator
then it is under
a u.s supported democratic democratic
government in iraq
democracy is not the solution everywhere
many people's many cultures
are simply incompatible with democracy
you cannot have a one size fits all
solution everywhere in the world
when you have a culture like you have in
afghanistan democracy doesn't work there
democracy cannot work there
that culture is more amenable to sharia
law that that is a fact that you cannot
deny no matter whatever is your opinion
about sharia law
they desire it then they're good they're
gonna have it now
right
and this is the similar thing can be
seen in libya for example the americans
bombed democracy into libya but the
standards of living the law and order
situation was much better under the
brutal dictator
muammar gaddafi then it is under
whatever regime is there in libya today
that is
an undeniable fact i know
muammar gaddafi was a bloodthirsty
tyrant
and yet the country was better off under
him
so certain cultures need that sort of
leadership in order to
live in a in an orderly manner
that's just the way it is
and currently
the culture that is
prevalent in afghanistan among the
people
is such that they desire sharia law they
reject western style democracy
and the thing is this the afghan
government the u.s backed afghan
government
was able to maintain some semblance of
order
in the regions it governed but there was
no justice
there is a difference between order and
justice
when somebody does a riot and targets a
particular community
then imposing order means you quell the
riot
but giving justice means you punish the
guilty
in afghanistan there was no
no justice there was only order under
the afghan government
under sharia law
the taliban have promised to punish
everybody who is guilty the afghans
actually welcomed that because there was
no justice under
the
western-backed afghan government
and in the 1990s no matter how brutal
the taliban rule was at least there was
instant justice in whatever medieval
form it was but there was justice they
did provide justice according to their
understanding
of justice so for afghanistan for the
people of afghanistan for the common man
perhaps woman man mostly it is a welcome
change
so that is the fact the undeniable fact
in afghanistan they do desire sharia law
rahul asks what is pakistan's role in
all of these developments the taliban
officers had safe houses in pakistan
does it mean the pakistan government was
was aware of aiding these militants and
decided to do nothing about it
what about the future etc look the
pakistan government was not aware of
aiding the militants they were aiding
the militants
right
like i explained some time ago that
taliban is a creation of the pakistanis
but the main question is what is
pakistan's role
in the taliban's victory the taliban
have one afghanistan
more than 95 of the country is under
taliban control today this has happened
on all in the last week or so
what is pakistan's role in taliban's
victory
and surprisingly
pakistan has had almost no role in this
in the events of the past
week or even the past month
the pakistani isi
wanted there to be a bloody
war in afghanistan a bloody civil war
and they wanted a great deal of
resistance with taliban from the afghan
army
and that is where when if if that had
happened then the isi would have been
able to help the taliban and send
regular pakistani
army people in the guise of taliban to
assist the taliban and then the taliban
would have been able to eventually take
over the country and kabul with the help
of the isi
that would make the isi completely in
control of the taliban and of
afghanistan
what's happened
is that the taliban have
spread through the country
marched through the country in lightning
fast manner and there has been almost no
opposition to taliban
and therefore this taliban victory has
come
without any help from pakistan it makes
the taliban de facto independent from
pakistan
that is
what's happened
so as of today the pakistani isi is
stunned at what's happened
they have all of a sudden
overnight lost control of the taliban
and the question is who is
controlling the taliban today that is
the big question
what understandings
does the taliban have with which
geopolitical
players that is the big question but
what is clear is that the pakistan isi
is no longer
in
any kind of significant control
of the taliban
today
atharva asks can we expect any change in
governance from the taliban is this a
direct capture of afghanistan by
pakistan
as taliban has had a strong hand in
the taliban so no
this is by no means a capture of
afghanistan by pakistan the intention
the objective of the isi in creating the
taliban was to use it to capture
afghanistan and to create to turn
afghanistan into their strategic
backyard it is the doctrine of strategic
depth
but what's happened the events of the
past month the past week have completely
turned the tables
it is not the pakistanis who have
captured afghanistan it is the taliban
as an independent entity suppose which
looks like an independent entity which
has captured afghanistan
so that's what's happened any uh change
in governance from the taliban well the
taliban this time around they promised
to be more they seem to be promising to
be
uh
more reasonable than the last time then
the 1990s they are holding press
conferences they are making the right
noises they are saying the right words
we will allow women to
to
study we will allow girls to study we
will not stop women from moving around
as long as they wear that whatever dress
that is
the
yeah whatever it is called etc so they
are making the right noises they're
making the right they're giving us right
signals
but it is also emerging that they are
engaging in various
reprisals
and they are killing their enemies etc
in various parts of the country far away
from kabul far away from the cameras
so that is of course happening so i
would not expect a great deal of change
in the way that taliban will govern the
country they will
seek to impose very quickly
law and order sharia law in the country
so that will be a big change from what
was happening earlier
but the level of brutality might not
change
very significantly
sonia asks is the un doing anything to
help afghanistan and do you think there
will be an exodus of afghan refugees
to india
what is the u.n united nations doing in
afghanistan the u.n is uninvolved in
afghanistan the u.n is doing absolutely
nothing in afghanistan isn't it the duty
and the entire purpose of the u.n to
help people who are in need to prevent
wars from happening and to mediate in
these conflicts it is the very reason
for the existence of the united nations
and yet
the u.n is entirely and completely
uninvolved in afghanistan they have been
making they may have been making some
pronouncements they may have been
tweeting about something about
afghanistan but it's just words
it's like gandhi saying i am against
partition but not actually doing
anything against partition
words
are meaningless unless they are backed
up with
actions so the u.n is doing nothing in
afghanistan like i have said many times
in the past any multilateral
organization
exists
to serve the interests of its most
powerful
members
and the most powerful members in the u.n
are currently the us and to some extent
china
so the u.s wants to withdraw from
afghanistan the us wants these events to
play out as they are happening right now
so the un is essentially
allowing it to happen
the u.n is
a tool
in the u.s toolbox
will there be an exodus of afghan
refugees to india well it can't happen
unless there is a direct land connection
between india and afghanistan on the map
we have a border with afghanistan but
that part of our territory is currently
occupied illegally by pakistan
so if there is to be a refugee influx
into into india from afghanistan it will
only be possible if it happens through
pakistan occupied kashmir and gilgam i
don't think the pakistanis will allow
this
so i don't see any exodus of afghan
refugees into india unless
it is with the agreement of the indian
government and the taliban in which case
they could come by air so recently there
have been a few flights coming from
kabul to india
with the approval of the taliban in
which several
afghan mps members of parliament came
into india they reached delhi and they
will be
given
accommodation somewhere in delhi i
suppose
so that is also
happening only because the taliban has
agreed to it there is some sort of
understanding
between india and the taliban as to
allowing these afghans into india
anita says
can the new northern alliance
in punjab
overthrow the taliban regime
it is extremely unlikely that the
northern alliance would be able to
overthrow the taliban regime so let me
show the map
where is this thing happening
okay here is afghanistan let us search
for punjuice
afghanistan it is quite close to kabul
this is the pandeshire valley
of afghanistan
as you can see it is
barely 30-40 kilometers from kabul
now if you see the satellite image you
will see that it is a mountainous region
so it is a valley in the
upper ciena mountain range or the hindu
kosh mountain range
that is punjashir so it is quite
difficult to access so it has these
natural fortifications and defenses
but the problem with the northern
alliance which is there right now in
this valley in the panjushir valley
the problem they are facing is that they
are surrounded on all sides
by taliban held territory
so they have no supply lines
if you are resisting something like the
taliban you need supplies you need arms
you need ammunition you need fuel you
need food you need money
and for that you need
a supply line
if you are surrounded on all sides by
the enemy
then all your supply lines are cut off
and that is the situation
the uh
northern alliance in the panshir valley
finds itself in
it is completely surrounded by the by
the afghan taliban
so
unfortunately i do not see them holding
out for very long it seems to be
a doomed enterprise
we know that um
politician
the afghan tajik politician is currently
in this region in the panchayat valley
he has vowed to not surrender to the
taliban
i wish him the best i wish him the best
of luck but i do not unfortunately
seeing this going very well
unfortunately because
the ground situation is such that they
are totally surrounded and they have no
way of getting any supplies
so it is umura saleh and it is the
who are
in this region they are
trying to resist the taliban but i do
not see this lasting very long
unfortunately
yuvraj garg asks
after this event what is the objective
of the islamic america of afghanistan as
a country
maybe for the next 10 years or so
so what you're asking is what is the
what are the taliban's objectives over
the next 10 years
after
they have won the war and they have
taken over afghanistan
so so the taliban will want to normalize
the situation in afghanistan they would
want to stamp out all resistance first
of all
they would like to consolidate their
hold over the country or the entire
country right now they are in possession
of all the major cities and all the all
the roads that connect these cities
but there may be regions in the
mountains in the hills in the valleys
and rural areas where they may not have
a complete
presence
so they will want to consolidate their
hold
over the country so that is going to
take some time
that is number one
and they will also want to
ensure that any potential or possible
external influence
in the country
is stopped or prevented so as you know
the taliban
is a creation
of pakistan
and the pakistanis have their own agenda
in afghanistan
the taliban are see that
the pakistanis created the taliban
as an islamist organization
they wanted the taliban to have
an islamist
identity
the common factor they wanted the
taliban to believe in was islam
but they recruited the taliban only from
the pashtuns
so the taliban have morphed into a
pashtun organization
and their agenda is now pashtun
nationalism
so they want to
consolidate their hold
and control over the entire country
and they want to ensure that these
external forces that seek to manipulate
them and seek to influence events in the
country
that influence goes away
that is their agenda they also would
like the world to recognize them as the
legitimate authority and government in
afghanistan
so that is where geopolitics comes in
and then they have certain other
nationalistic agendas as well which are
left over
from the history of the indian
subcontinent
the duran line
so that's where the fun and games
eventually begin
for which country is the taliban an
immediate threat
and does india need to continue their
infrastructure projects in afghanistan
after the talibans take over
let me answer the first question or the
second question first
should india continue its infrastructure
projects in afghanistan
as of now india should wait and watch
india should observe what's happening
and maybe have some sort of dialogue
with the principal actor or actors in
the country
and let's see how things go about that
india has gained a great amount of
goodwill in afghanistan because of all
the projects it has done
those projects have not been with the
intention of projecting power in
afghanistan or with the intention of
manipulating afghanistan they have
actually been projects that have
benefited the people of afghanistan
agriculture projects the dam etc and
much more it has all been
something that benefits the people of
afghanistan and every pashtun knows this
they all have an amount of goodwill and
warmth towards india including many many
of the taliban commanders
so
as of today india has done enough for
now
india needs to wait and watch and
conduct some sort of dialogue with the
principal actors
that's about question number two
question number one is for which country
is the taliban an immediate
that is a very good question
the taliban
is a threat for many countries
they are a terrorist organization they
are a un-designated terrorist outfit
i think the russians are quite wary of
the taliban because the see let's let's
see the map
uh the central asian region is
considered by russia to be its strategic
backyard
they consider this these are all the
former soviet republics
the former republic central asian
republics of the ussr
and the russians consider this to be
their
sphere of their their sphere of
influence
now so turkmenistan uzbekistan
kyrgyzstan et
are all considered by the russians to be
part of their
extended sphere of influence the russian
military does
military exercises regularly in these
countries
just a couple of weeks ago the russians
did a military exercise in tajikistan
just a handful of kilometers away from a
taliban outpost across the border in
afghanistan
so the russians are quite wary about a
potential spillover of taliban
activities
or influence
into the central asian region which
they have a great amount of interest in
that's number one
number two the chinese are also very
worried
that
the xinjiang region of china could
witness a spillover
of the taliban influence and that could
lead to
another upsurge in
separatist activities in xinjiang as we
know
this xinjiang region is actually east
turkestan it is occupied by china the
natives of this region are the uyghurs
and we know what the chinese have been
doing with the uyghurs
so the egos have been fighting this uh
armed conflict with the chinese there
have been many terrorist incidents etc
you could call it terrorism you could
call it freedom fighting whatever you
want to call it but the chinese are
facing a serious insurgency in xinjiang
and the taliban victory in afghanistan
could
could spill over into xinjiang it could
provide some sort of
some sort of impetus to the xinjiang
freedom struggle so the chinese also
perceive a great amount of threat
from the taliban
now let's come south
which country
sees taliban as an immediate threat of
course it is pakistan
we spoke about the taliban pakistan
which is in this region if you can see
my mouse pointer
the northern and western regions of
pakistan the
the pashtun regions of pakistan the
tribal regions of pakistan
so and the
afghan taliban do not recognize this
line
the duran line
as the border between pakistan and
afghanistan they have a territorial
dispute
with pakistan
the pashtuns have never recognized the
duran line
which was drawn in the late 1890s by the
british the pashtuns have never
recognized that as the border between
india
and afghanistan so after independence
became the border between pakistan and
afghanistan
but many of these regions of pakistan
are pashtun majority regions
and the pashtuns
on both sides of the border
seek a unified pashtun country
pashtunistan
which would be part of afghanistan
so that is the problem for pakistan now
that the taliban have suddenly become
independent so to say
of pakistan
they will have their own nationalistic
agenda pashtun nationalism which does
not recognize the durham line
between pakistan and afghanistan and
they see the pakistani army the punjabi
army
as an occupying force
and what we are seeing
in the past few days is that in the
pakistani regions that are pashtun
majority in the villages you are seeing
taliban flags flying everywhere instead
of pakistan flags
and just a couple of days ago i hear
that the terrike taliban pakistan has
declared its allegiance
to the afghan taliban
so this could quickly
become a significant separatist movement
in pakistan
and that is why
the taliban is an immediate
clear and present threat for pakistan
itself today
that is the reality we are witnessing as
of today
okay okay
will the taliban be keen on integrating
khyber paktunwa
into afghanistan
pakistan exactly khaibar pakhtunwa is is
the basically let's read this region
uh kyber pakhtun where exactly is it
pakistan
all right so it is
the northern and western regions of
pakistan and even parts of balochistan
because the headquarters of the bucket
of the taliban is in quetta
balochistan so all of these regions
will be now
eyed by the taliban they will want to
incorporate eventually in the long term
all of these regions
into pastures
into afghanistan this is going to
possibly
spill over
into a conflict
in pakistan
we that the taliban pakistan have been
conducting terrorist organizations in
pakistan for the best part of two
decades and now that they are aligned
with the afghan taliban you could see an
upsurge in such events in various parts
of pakistan i hear yesterday itself
there was a
attack in balochistan i think in gwadar
in which
nine chinese
nationals were
killed
in the terrorist attack
so this could all be an outcome of what
we are witnessing in afghanistan the
taliban tagore of afghanistan so they
will definitely have a long term
objective of integrating the khyber
pathu and various other pashtun majority
regions into their own territory so this
could become a significant territorial
dispute between afghanistan and pakistan
why is china and russia accepting
taliban as the government of afghanistan
china we know what it's doing in the
with the muslims
but it's supporting an islamic emirate
in the backyard and why is russia
willing to recognize the taliban as well
look it's nothing to do with principles
and all that
geopolitics is about real politics it's
about the national interest
what is the chinese interest in
afghanistan
number one they don't want any spillover
of terrorism in xinjiang that's number
one
number two the chinese regard
afghanistan as a potential connecting
region
for the
china-pakistan economic corridor and
also for the chinese belt and road
infrastructure
so if afghanistan is
everything goes well then they would
like to use afghanistan for connectivity
so they would like to
build someone's infrastructure through
afghanistan so that is interest number
two and number three we know that
afghanistan is sitting on at least a
trillion dollars worth of mineral
resources and the chinese want to
extract and exploit
this mineral wealth of afghanistan so
that is the interest that china has in
afghanistan and they are happy to
work with any government
that is there in afghanistan if it is
taliban they will work with the taliban
why not
it works for them it is in china's
national interest to work with whoever
is in power in afghanistan
now when it comes to russia they also
are
very of the potential spillover of
terrorist activities into the central
asian region they don't want that they
have
been fighting terrorism for a very long
time
so they want to contain that within
afghanistan that's number one and number
two they also want to possibly uh expand
their sphere of influence in the region
and they also want to sample
taste some of that mineral wealth that
afghanistan has to offer
so that is why russia also is very much
willing to work with taliban because it
is in russia's national interest to work
with whoever is in power in afghanistan
that is the simple reason why the
chinese and the russians
are
very willing to support the taliban and
to work with them
shivashish says u.s russia china what
are the objectives on the current issue
and who will benefit the most okay so we
spoke about russia and china
what about the united
states that is the big question
does the u.s
have no more interest in this region
what what is the deal with the u.s
that's that's the question
they have definitely left afghanistan
they have withdrawn from there they had
built up an entire uh
infrastructure
of logistics in central asia
a northern network by which they were
able to supply their their troops in
afghanistan
after things cooled off with pakistan
that entire infrastructure has also been
mostly dismantled so it looks like the
american influence in central asia and
afghanistan is almost over the
pakistanis themselves are now in the
chinese camp so america
doesn't even have good relations with
pakistan anymore
so what is the american objective are
they have they simply given up on the
region
not quiet
see we know very well that the
pakistanis were supporting the taliban
all this time
they were supporting the taliban even
when the american soldiers were being
killed by the taliban and the americans
know this very well
right
so one of the objectives
of the u.s
see we know that the u.s has handed over
the country on a platter
to the taliban the afghan army for some
reason has not given any resistance to
the
taliban and all of this equipment has
fallen into taliban hands so it looks
like there has been some sort of
agreement
between the americans and the taliban to
hand over the country to the taliban
and the deal is the taliban
will capture the country so fast that it
will become free from pakistan influence
to a great extent
and then
if the americans recognize the taliban
and they give them legitimacy
then the taliban will become strong in
their command over afghanistan
and then maybe they want the chinese to
get embroiled in this and suffer a
setback
but i think the main
objective of the americans is to
punish the pakistanis
for the way they betrayed the americans
over the past 20 years the pakistani
army and the isi is personally
responsible for the deaths of hundreds
if not thousands of american soldiers at
the hands of the taliban
i think the americans want to
give it back to the pakistanis by making
the taliban bleed pakistan now
because of the territorial dispute they
have
so this could be the overall american
objective
they want to
destabilize pakistan now
as a payback
and the americans now are in this big
competition big rivalry with the chinese
so they now need india on their side to
offset and counter balance the chinese
so maybe india also has some role in
this we know that the americans have not
been targeted by the taliban there are
still many american nationals there
there are american reporters there the
taliban are keeping their hands off
they have not touched any american they
have allowed the american
military operations air force operations
to continue in evacuating people from
kabul airport they have not interfered
in that
the taliban have also not interfered in
any indian activities they have allowed
indian citizens to come back to india
they have allowed the indian air force
to land in kabul take out indian
citizens so there is clearly something
going on the taliban seems to have some
sort of understanding with the americans
with the indians
something is going on something is
cooking and i think the country that
will
that will suffer the most from all of
this
could very well be pakistan
it could be
the start of something bad for pakistan
that is the feeling that i get from all
this
harshit asks what could be the impact of
the taliban on
india
in national security and border disputes
with pakistan
and so on will the pakistanis fund
talibans and use them to attack india
so the question is does the taliban pose
a threat to india
will it interfere in some way in kashmir
i do not see the taliban posing any
threat
to india directly
i do not see the taliban having any
desire to interfere in kashmir they have
already officially stated that they see
the kashmir dispute as a bilateral
matter between india and pakistan
the taliban's objective is to
is to control the country to consolidate
its hold over the country
and their real objective
long term will be to take back the
pashtun areas from pakistan
i do not see the taliban
as having any sort of
problem with india
india
on the map it it
has a shared border with afghanistan but
that region is currently held by the
pakistanis
so we don't even have a common border
with the afghans and therefore we do not
pose a threat to the afghans if you look
at the raj mandala theory two countries
which have a common border they pose a
threat to each other
in reality we currently do not have a
land connection with afghanistan so the
taliban doesn't see india as a threat
they see pakistan as their biggest
threat so i do not see any impact
of taliban
on india's national security recently we
have seen
some terrorists in kashmir
being caught with rpgs rocket propelled
grenades i think it is just a ploy by
pakistan to make india think that there
is some taliban influences in this the
taliban have their hands full in their
own country in afghanistan i think that
the taliban also have some sort of
understanding
india and the u.s
so i don't see
any threat
at present to india
from the taliban
kavita says you often talk about
chanakya's version of the world
how would chanakya deal with taliban
and the kind of terrorism
we see today
very good question how would chanakya
deal with
the taliban
okay
this is what chanakya would ask himself
a
what is india's national interest
and where do india's biggest
threats come from
number two
what is the taliban's
national interest
and where does the taliban see its
biggest threat coming from
india's national interest
is
to reclaim the whole of kashmir
india's biggest threats are pakistan and
china
the taliban's national interest is to
consolidate their hold over the country
to reclaim pakistan occupied afghanistan
and their biggest threat in competitor
is pakistan
so chanakya would say that
i have this national interest and i have
these threats the taliban has this
national interest and they have these
threats do we have any kind of
convergence between these two
we both see
pakistan as our biggest threat we both
have territorial disputes
with pakistan
my enemy is pakistan
the taliban's enemy is pakistan why
can't we work together my enemies
enemies my friend
i don't care what taliban's ideology is
i don't care that they want sharia law
it has nothing to do with me it is their
internal matter
i
their national interest does seem to
have some convergence with my national
interest
so why can't we work together
that is how vishnu gupta chanakya would
see the world
this sort of
realistic approach has nothing to do
with morality with ethics
it is all about real politic it's all
about
pursuing your national interest it's all
destroying the common enemy that is how
chanakya would deal with the taliban he
would see them as an instrument that he
should work with
in destabilizing
and fragmenting
the common enemy which is pakistan and
that is why i do not see this i i know
the taliban takeover is a very bad thing
for many afghan people
especially those who are westernized and
who did not want sharia law it is a bad
thing for women who will now have extra
impositions on them
but from
a cold
hard geopolitical angle
it may actually be a good thing for
india
so that's what india needs to work with
some says what should india do now
should india support umrulla saleh to
give strength to the northern alliance
etc or should india shake hands with the
taliban for short-term peace india
should not seek anything in the short
term
all our national interest objectives
have to be long-term objectives we
should think in the term in in terms of
decades
what do we want to achieve in the next
decade and two decades i have always
said that india needs to
give itself a maximum of 20 years
to balkanize and fragment pakistan into
its component pieces
india needs to retake gilgamesh pakistan
and pakistan pakistan kashmir
we can give pashtun islam back to the
afghans
and we can have an independent sin
independent balochistan independent
punjab
etc
that's what india needs to achieve in
maximum 20 years
so
who will help india in doing this will
umla saleh or the northern alliance be
able to do it they are surrounded on all
sides
what is the point of supporting them i
am i know it's it is quite cynical and
heartless to say this
but as the leader of a country you
cannot
think with your heart you have to think
in a cold calculative manner
you have to do things from the
perspective of your long-term national
interest and india's national interest
is not going to be served by supporting
a losing cause
so india will be
it will be interesting if the indian
government finds ways of cooperating and
collaborating with the taliban
the pashtuns
in
doing what is best for the entire region
the pakistan
the pakistani regime
is a terrorist organization
the pakistan army is a terrorist
organization they are nuclear armed
terrorists they are they are a threat
for the entire region they are a threat
for for afghanistan and for india
india and afghanistan should join hands
and dismantle this threat
so i would say that india should
seek
ways of
should explore ways of cooperating
with the afghans with the pashtuns
in
fulfilling and furthering our common
national interests
krishna says if india wills can we wipe
out the taliban how do we do it what
should be india's afghan card for the
next 20 years and future
can the afghan diaspora in india help us
in any way in the future should we
engage with the northern
alliance
for the next 20 years
it is in india's interest
to have a peaceful
stable
afghanistan
in the past indian prime ministers have
said that we want a peaceful stable
pakistan people like ik gujarat etc
that is the last thing we need
a peaceful stable pakistan is a bigger
threat for india it's a bigger threat
for afghanistan what india should seek
over the next 20 years
is a strong
peaceful stable afghanistan that is
friendly with india it doesn't matter if
the taliban is ruling afghanistan we
have excellent relations with saudi
arabia where they have sharia law
or islamic law we have excellent
relations with the uae
with qatar and many other islamic
countries
we can have the same sort of excellent
relationship with afghanistan as well
even if it is under an islamist regime i
don't see any problem with that
india should seek
a strong stable peaceful and friendly
afghanistan over the next 20 years and
the only way of achieving this objective
of a strong peaceful friendly and stable
afghanistan
is by
balkanizing the threat the common thread
to both the countries which is pakistan
so that's what india needs to do why
should we wipe out the taliban the
taliban posed no threat to india
none whatsoever so i don't see any
reason why india would want to
wipe out or target the taliban in any
way unless they would be stupid enough
to try and interfere in india i don't
think they're stupid people i think they
are very smart people
how can the afghan diaspora in india
help us no no not at all
should we engage with the northern with
the northern alliance i don't think so
the northern alliance
is uh
not going to last very long sadly
omkar says will taliban take over
pakistan in the future arnab says will
tariq taliban
be a headache for the pakistanis now
that the taliban are back in power
i don't think the taliban will be able
to take over the whole of pakistan in
the future
the punjabis hate pakistan
the taliban the taliban are a pashtun
movement the punjabis and the pashtuns
have a very old rivalry
they have a very very old enmity that
goes back to the time of
dali
it goes back to the time when ahmad shah
abdali
helped the iranian
king and adarsha invade and sack india
and it goes back to the time of maharaja
ranjit singh when maharaja ranjitsik was
able to subdue the afghans
the pashtuns so there is this bitter
rivalry between the pashtuns and the
punjabis
the pashtuns the taliban
have taken help from the pakistan army
the isi who are all punjabis
because they had to
but now that they have their own country
and they've been able to win it on their
own
without any help from the punjabis
they will want to
pursue their pashtun nationalistic
agenda
and we have a strong taliban presence
in pakistan that the taliban pakistan
which is now aligned with the afghan
taliban and also
let us not forget
that there is a significant pashtun
population throughout pakistan now
karachi is has almost become a pashtun
majority city
so the pakistanis could be in a great
deal of trouble i don't think the
taliban will be able to take over the
whole of pakistan
but i don't see
i see
a civil war happening in pakistan in the
very near future
so yes the territory taliban pakistan
will be a very big headache for the
pakistanis
they could take over conceivably
significant portions of pakistan
especially the western and northern
parts
the pakistan army will definitely fight
back
so that's why i say there could be a
civil war in the coming days
this could very possibly my friends be
the beginning
of the end for pakistan
if india and the us and the afghans we
get together and we play our cards right
that is definitely a possibility
okay
let's take a look at
some live questions
if you have questions ask me now
okay do we have any questions
okay this is by aloki singh
can pakistan manipulate the taliban in
terms of islam and religion to make
taliban stand against india the taliban
are not stupid they are a pashtun
nationalist movement they are muslims
they will impose their own form of islam
sunni islam sharia et cetera in
afghanistan but they do not want any
interference from the punjabis
they see the pakistanis as punjabis
because the punjabis run the army in the
isi and they
run the whole country so
that old rivalry
and nationalistic identity will now come
to the fore i don't think the isi
will be able to manipulate the taliban
see how do you manipulate somebody
you manipulate somebody if they depend
on you
for money
for arms for ammunition for training
and all that
if you have that sort of control on
somebody
then you can manipulate those people
now the taliban may get funds from china
they make they will definitely get funds
from china
they will also get funds from russia
conceivably
they may be getting funds from the us
and from various other places iran may
also be a factor in this by the way the
afghanistan afghanistan has a
significant border with iran
so
the the pakistanis could very much find
themselves sidelined very fast they may
already be sidelined in this matter
so
i don't see the pakistanis the isi
being able to significantly manipulate
the taliban in any way because the
taliban are no longer controlled by them
they are no longer beholden to the isi
so let's take some more questions
questions about afghanistan not about
history
saraswati but no thank you not today
says is taliban backed by america still
america helped isis by dropping web from
dropping weapons and vehicles
see the americans
use various groups like these
as
temporary
tools to achieve their geopolitical
short-term geopolitical objectives
saddam hussein was once
an agent of the united states they used
saddam hussein this brutal iraqi
dictator
to bleed iran
and when saddam hussein was no longer
useful you know what they did to him
similarly they used
the taliban they used the afghan
mujahideen they used various
[Music]
terrorist outfits in the middle east
in north africa
the americans will use any terrorist
organization
for short for short periods of time as
long as it fulfills their short-term
geopolitical objectives
is the taliban still backed by the
americans it is a possibility they will
not admit it but it is a possibility
if you look at the way things have
happened
it is definitely a possibility
okay
what else do we have
good question by rj do you see the
taliban attacking china for those
muslims and concentration camps in china
the taliban are very
smart people
they are very clear about what their
objectives are their objective is to
serve is to consolidate their power in
afghanistan
and to
further the agenda of the pashtun
national interest
so their main problem is the pashtun
territories that are occupied by
pakistan
that is the main problem they have they
do not seek
to enter into a conflict
with
an enormous country like china
with whom they do have a small
shared border via tibet and xinjiang
so they do not wish to enter into a new
conflict with a country that can
conceivably defeat them very easily
so the taliban will not interfere in
chinese occupied
east turkestan
they will
seek to have a peaceful border and good
relations with the chinese
their bone of contention is pakistan the
pakistanis have been bleeding the
pashtuns for decades
the punjabis have been bleeding the
vashtons for centuries
that is the blood rivalry they will seek
to avenge sooner or later maybe sooner
if they are helped by external forces
okay what else do we have
what else do we have
kapil asks
what will happen to india and indians if
it takes up the mantle of the usa
and deploys the indian military in
afghanistan for counter-terrorism
operations basically replace the usa
my question is
how does such
an action
help india's national interest
does the taliban pose a threat to india
no
the taliban have made it very clear they
have no intention to interfere in any
form in india
the taliban have allowed the indian
embassy staff and other indians to
peacefully depart from afghanistan they
have allowed the indian air force to
land in kabul take people out without
any trouble they have been cooperating
they have been saying the right things
thus far they have done absolutely
nothing against india
so i don't see why india should regard
the taliban
as a terrorist outfit we should regard
them
we should regard
an organization as a terrorist outfit if
it targets india and indian interests
if it does not target india
if it does not target indian interests
then it is not our concern what else
they do
and therefore india should not regard
the taliban
as a terrorist outfit as long as it does
not target india or indian people or
indian interests
and therefore i do not see it
necessary
or fruitful or desirable
for india to deploy its military in
afghanistan it would be a very
stupid move
similar to what rajiv gandhi did in sri
lanka it's pointless
the taliban could actually be an ally of
india like i have been saying
so
yeah so india should not do any of that
there is no need for india to try and
replace the usa
it is pointless
what else do we have
[Music]
pawan says what are the indirect threats
that the taliban poses to india
is it rays of
motivation of separatist forces
the taliban does not pose any threat to
india they their agenda is not india
their agenda has to consolidate their
consolidate their power in their own
country and once they are able to do
that they will want to reclaim their
territories from pakistan it does not
pose a threat to india
it does not as far as i understand it
does not seem to have any connections
with
the
terrorist organizations that the
pakistanis have created in kashmir
so i don't see it posing any significant
threat to india
as long as india handles the situation
properly
so this is a good opportunity for
india akshay says will it not be
hypocritical for india to recognize the
taliban when they consider kashmiri
mujahideen as terrorists
it has nothing to do it has nothing to
do with principles
politics geopolitics
is replete with hypocrisy the biggest
hypocrites in the world
are the americans
and the chinese
why should we be left behind let us
embrace hypocrisy for the sake of the
national interest what is more important
tell me please
is the national interest more importance
or the way the world sees you
do you want to look
principled and non-hypocritical or do
you want to pursue your national
interest what is more important
i don't give two hoots about how india
is perceived worldwide
india should prioritize its national
interest even if it looks hypocritical
that's what the americans have been
doing for for decades that's what the
russians have been doing for decades
that's what the chinese have always done
india should also do the same only
pursue your national interest
play the hard geopolitical game
recognize the taliban as long as it does
not pose a threat to india and target
the kashmiri mujahideen and various
terrorist organizations as terrorists
that's what india should do
perception doesn't matter let the world
call us hypocrites
20 years down the line we will have a
stronger country and those claims of
hypocrisy will be long forgotten
sumit says
will the taliban survive in afghanistan
will it remain stable as the people of
afghanistan do not like the taliban
uh i just uh
we know that the the 99 percent of the
of the afghan population wants sharia
law
and the
ashraf ghani government did not
believe in sharia law they did not give
sharia a lot of the people it is the
taliban who is giving sharia law so what
does the people what do the people of
afghanistan want
they want the taliban my friends
the taliban will survive in afghanistan
they have the guns they have the
firepower they have the support they
have everything
what can the people do even if they
don't like the taliban what can they do
the people of india over the past
thousand years did not like the turks
but the turks were able to stay in india
and occupy india
until the 17th century
so even though the people did not like
them even though they were so brutal in
barbaric they were able to occupy india
now the taliban on the other hand
actually has support among the pashtun
people
and among the 99 of afghans who want
sharia law
so i don't see any problem for taliban
in surviving and even thriving
in afghanistan
should india shake hands with the
taliban to solve the pok issue
in return for india's support in the
united nations
india should support the taliban in the
u.n
contingent on them
doing what we want
with vis-a-vis pakistan
india needs to ensure that pakistan is
balkanized in the next 10 to 20 years
if the taliban takes steps in that
regard
in reclaiving pastures etc and as long
as they are
favorably inclined towards india as long
as they don't interfere in india in any
way i don't see why india should not
support them as the legitimate
government of afghanistan
okay harsh says what is the chinese role
in the overall collapse
that was orchestrated
ghani leaving with the money
by then denying the possibility of
collapse etc is it all due to chinese
influence
i don't think china has any role thus
far in what has happened
everything that has happened until this
point
has been orchestrated by the americans
they were
in control of large parts of the country
their military
was in control
of significant portions of the country
they have a very powerful air force that
can wipe out any taliban presence if
they want
so it was the americans
who were
in control of the territory
to a large extent
of afghanistan it is their choice
that they have left in the manner that
they have
it is their choice that they left behind
all this
cash all these weapons
and everything else to the taliban
and it seems to have been their choice
that the afghan army
allowed the taliban to take over so i
don't see china has having anything to
do with this
but yes now the chinese will want to get
involved in this and maybe it is a trap
for the chinese set by the americans
okay one more question
one more question
shashank says why can't india just go on
and conquer pakistan pakistan occupied
kashmir
things have to be done step by step
you
you cannot get ahead of yourself you
cannot take
rash decisions everything has to be
calculated
well thought out well planned out
you cannot act emotionally
this is a very big move to go back and
conquer pakistan occupied kashmir take
it back it should be done at the right
time
it should be done
and when is the right time for that the
right time is when pakistan is very weak
right now the pakistanis have the
support of china
they have nuclear weapons so right now
would not be a good time to
do this thing the chinese may also get
in involved in this matter right now but
in the future if pakistan is in the
middle of a civil war if it is
destabilized in the northern and western
borders with afghanistan
and maybe if it is on the brink of being
fragmented by because of these forces
that would be the right time to go and
take back pok and do various other
things
so what india needs is patience we have
waited 70 plus years let's wait another
5 10 15 years and do the things
at the right time
when things are when the time is right
so as of today india needs to wait and
watch
do things behind the scenes
shake hands with the right actors
on the geopolitical stage
and bide its time
india should give itself a 20-year
target
of clearing the neighborhood of all the
problems
at least on the western border
and this could be the beginning of that
this could very much be
the beginning of the end of pakistan
possibly if india plays its cards right
okay
so that brings us to an end of this
session my friends thank you so much
for all your questions very good very
interesting questions thank you so much
so
we we end this here and i will see you
very soon i will see you
in tomorrow's
history session
until then take care have a good day
have a good night
bye